Okay so picking up on the top of ח"א, Chet Aleph, אמר
רב זירא אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Zeira Amar Shmuel. Now that we're
done with those nice digressions about צדיקים Tzaddikim not eating טרייף Treif
food, we get back to our major theme, which is שחיטה. Shechita.
We've looked at questions about some people's validity about a כותי Kuti
and a מומר Mumar and so on. Now we're going to start
focusing a little bit on the act of שחיטה. Shechita. So let's
take a look. אמר רב זירא אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Zeira Amar
Shmuel, so Rav Zeira said in the name of Shmuel, ליבן סכין
ושחט בה, Liben sakin veshachat bah, you made your knife white hot,
you put it over fire, and you used it to שחט. Shecht.
So the question is, are you שחט-ing Shecht-ing the animal? Is the
sharpness of the knife cutting the throat, or are you burning the
throat, is the heat of the knife cutting the throat? So he
says שחיטתו כשרה, Shechitatos kesheira, it is a good שחיטה. Shechita. חידודא
קודם לליבונא, Chiduda kodem lelibuna,
the sharpness precedes the heat. So yes, it's white hot, but the
sharpness of the knife will cut the throat before the heat is
able to have an effect. So it actually is a good שחיטה.
Shechita. So much for צער בעלי חיים. Tzar ba'alei chayim. So now
the גמרא Gemara says ואיכא צדדים, Ve'ika tzedadim, one minute, so I
get that as you start cutting, the sharpness of the knife cuts,
but as you move the knife into the throat, so the heat
is burning the side, the inner opening that you've created, and that's
making the animal presumably a טריפה. Treifa. Either it's burning the סימנים
Simanim and it's
actually finishing off the trachea and esophagus before your cut gets there,
or at least it's making the animal a טריפה Treifa and it's
having an effect on the animal before you've finished the שחיטה. Shechita.
So what about that? So the גמרא Gemara says בית השחיטה מרווח
רווח. Beit hashechita mivrach ravach. No, when you שחט, Shecht, the, you
know, when you cut in, it opens up. So it's not like
you're cutting in and it's a thin, it's a thin sort of
cut. As you're cutting, the wound opens, so the heat of the
knife is not directly touching the skin. Only the sharpness of the
knife at the contact point is touching, but the sides of the
knife, right, is this clear? Meaning, if this is, can you give
me that white pad over there? Right, if this is your knife,
right, so the sides are what really has the heat, not the
tip. The tip, I mean, has a little heat, but it's a
very thin tip. So as you're cutting through, right, the sides here,
the question is aren't they touching skin? And the answer is no,
because as you're שחט-ing Shecht-ing and cutting through, the skin opens up
like that. So the sides of the knife are actually not touching.
That's other observations? Yes, possibly.
Oh,
it's sealing the wound as you're, that's an interesting question. That's an
interesting question. So the blood isn't coming out. So actually, you know,
technically speaking, the שחיטה Shechita does not cut, have to cut any
veins or arteries. The שחיטה Shechita just cuts the trachea and esophagus.
Now you're supposed to cut, what's the main artery here, the carotid
artery, right, in order to drain the blood, to make it easier
in terms of removing the blood afterwards. But in terms of actually
הכשר שחיטה, Hechsher shechita, it's not about getting the blood out, believe
it or not, it's about cutting the trachea and esophagus. So that
would not פסל Passel the שחיטה, Shechita, might make it harder to
get the blood out afterwards.
So the גמרא Gemara says איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, they raise the
following question, ליבן שפוד והיכה בו. Liben shipud vehika bo.
So now we're going to talk about an analogous case, not relating
to שחיטה. Shechita. If somebody makes a like a poker white hot,
some type of metal stick, and he smacks somebody with it, משום
שחין נידון או משום מכוה נידון. Mishum shechin nidon o mishum michva
nidon. Is it a שחין Shechin or is it like a wound,
or is it a מכוה, Michva, a burn? What's the difference? These
words שחין Shechin and מכוה Michva are taken from the תורה's Torah's
discussion about צרעת, Tzara'at, right, about what we call leprosy, and basically
talks about that if somebody has a wound or a burn and
as a result, you know, a white spot grows out there and
hair grows, that it's treated in certain ways for the laws of
צרעת. Tzara'at. So the גמרא Gemara wants to know which category does
this fall into? Okay, you smack the guy with this white-hot poker,
it's both a wound and a burn, which category does it fall
into? So the גמרא's Gemara's going to explain why this matters. למאי
נפקא
מינה, Lemai nafka mina, for what does this matter? לכדתניא, Lechid'tanya,
like we taught in the ברייתא, Braita, שחין ומכוה מטמאים בשבוע אחד
בשני סימנים בשיער לבן ובפשיון. Shechin umichva metama'im beshavua echad bishnei simanim
bese'ar lavan uvifisyon. So a lot of, most other spots of leprosy,
if they're, if you can't determine at the end of one week
whether it is or is not צרעת, Tzara'at, it hasn't spread or
whatever, you close it up for a second week and you give
it a second week to determine. However, if it is a spot
that is a result of either a wound or a burn and
it hasn't spread and doesn't have the hair,
the white hair at the end of one week, then the person
is טהור. Tahor. So it only has one week, so that's the
point of this ברייתא. Braita. שחין ומכוה, Shechin umichva, whether it's the
wound or a burn, but not just a spot that appeared on
its own, מטמאים בשבוע אחד, Metama'im beshavua echad, they only become טמא
Tamei at the end of one week. You would not close it
up for two weeks like you would do in a normal case.
בשני סימנים, Bishnei simanim, and there are two things to be looking
for, בשיער לבן Bese'ar lavan ובפשיון. uvifisyon. So that's the point of
this ברייתא, braita, שחין ומכוה, shechin u'michva, whether it's the wound or
a burn, but not just a spot that appeared on its own,
מטמא בשבוע אחד. mitame b'shavua echad. They only become טמא tamei at
the end of one week. You would not close it up for
two weeks like you would do in a normal case, בשני סימנים,
bishnei simanim, and there are two things to be looking for, שיער
לבן, se'ar lavan, white hair that grows there, ובפסיון, u'vifisayon, and it
spread. Okay, so those are the things that would determine that it
would become a, that it would be leprous. ולמה חלקן הכתוב? v'lama
chilkan hakatuv? Now so far it looks like they have the same
law. So what do I care how I call it? So why
does the Torah speak about having two separate פסוקים, psukim, one dealing
with the wound and one with the burn? לומר, lomar, to tell
you שאין מצטרפין זה עם זה, she'ein mitztarfin ze im ze, because
there's a minimum size for a spot of leprosy. It's כגריס, k'gris,
like the size of some type of a lentil bean. So let's
say I have a little spot based on a burn and a
little spot based on a wound, and they're right next to each
other, and they both and together they satisfy the requirements. It doesn't
matter. Since one is based on a wound and one is based
on a burn, they don't combine to be a leprous spot. Okay,
so now we're going to explain, so we're almost there to explaining
how our question matters. ותניא v'tanya or ותנן, v'tnan, we taught in
the משנה, mishna, איזו היא שחין ואיזו היא מכוה? eizo hi shechin
v'eizo hi michva? Which what is a wound and what is a
burn? לקה בעץ באבן, laka b'etz b'even, if you banged yourself with
a or was hit with wood or with a stone, בגפת בחמי
טבריה, b'gefet b'chamei Tverya, or גפת gefet which I am forgetting what
it is, some other type of a, let's see רש"י Rashi says.
Oh, רש"י Rashi says, oh, I see right. רש"י Rashi says that
you put it in, גפת gefet is like the type of lees
of of olives. So apparently even if you burn your hand or
burn your body, but it's a burn that's not due to fire
but through other sources of heat. So actually גפת gefet is one
of the things that you would actually according to the משנה mishna
put stuff in on שבת Shabbat to before שבת Shabbat to keep
it warm or you might have because these types of organic material
as they decompose release heat. So these would be a way of
actually getting heat produced you know something that would add heat. So
if you stuck it in that so you would get it you
got a mark because of the heat but it's not heat based
on fire.
That's that, where were we?
בחמי טבריה, b'chamei Tverya, or even hot water but it's hot from
underground springs like the hot waters of of Tiberias. ובכל דבר שלא
בא מחמת האור, u'v'chol davar shelo ba machamat ha'or, anything even if
it's not due to impact, but even if it's due to heat
but not heat based on fire, that is considered לאתויי l'atuyei which
includes even אבר מעיקרו, ever me'ikaro, if you take out some metal
from its original source, you mine metal and I guess some ore
is hot when it's originally mined, I don't know, does anybody know
this? It says lead when it's mined is hot. Anyway, anything that's
hot as long as it's not hot due to fire is a
is considered a שחין, shechin, is a wound. זהו שחין, zehu shechin,
that's a wound.
ואיזו היא מכוה? v'eizo hi michva? What is considered a burn? That's
specifically by fire. נכוה בגחלת, nichva b'gachelet, somebody that is burned by
a coal, ברמץ, b'remetz, or by ashes, hot ashes, בסיד
רותח, b'sid roteach, boiling plaster if it was heated by fire, ובגפסית
רותחת, u'v'gafsit rotachat, or גפסית gafsit which is another type of a
of a plaster that is been been heated up. Anything that either
is been fire or been heated by a fire, ובכל דבר הבא
מחמת האור, u'v'chol davar haba machamat ha'or, anything that comes as a
result of fire, לאתויי חמי האור, l'atuyei chamei ha'or, which would include
let's say water heated by fire, זו היא מכוה, zo hi michva,
that's a מכוה. michva. Okay, so we know there are these two
categories. We know the הלכות halachot are the same, that they have
one week to determine if they're leprous not two weeks, but we
know that they don't combine a half of each. Okay.
אבר מעיקרו, ever me'ikaro, maybe something like lava.
Oh,
that's interesting. That's interesting. Molten ore. Molten ore, that's interesting.
Hot but not heated
by fire like actually heated by the underground. That's interesting. Okay. ותניא,
v'tanya, okay, and here we're getting close to seeing how this matters
with how you categorize it since the laws are same. שחין ומכוה.
shechin u'michva. Let's say you have a wound that both was burn
a burn and a wound and due to impact or something that
wasn't fire. So how do you categorize it? אם שחין קודם למכוה,
im shechin kodem l'michva, if first it was a wound and then
afterwards it became a burn, בטלה מכוה את השחין, batla michva et
hashechin, you go basically you go by the latter. The burn nullifies
the שחין shechin status. אם מכוה קודמת לשחין, im michva kodemet l'shechin,
if first it was a burn and then it was a
wound, בטלה שחין את המכוה. batla shechin et hamichva. So the שחין
shechin nullifies the burn status. You go by the latter. All right,
so how is this going to be relevant for us? והכא היכי
דמי? v'hacha heichi dami? What would be the case for us? כגון
דהוה ביה חצי גריס שחין מעיקרא. k'gon d'hava bei chatzi gris shechin
me'ikara. Somebody started with a wound that had the signs of leprosy
that was half of the size required to make something leprous. It
was half of a גריס, gris, half the size of a lentil
bean. You started with a שחין shechin that was half the size.
And then what happened? והכא, v'hacha, I'm sorry, ואחוי ליה שפוד, v'achvei
lei shapud,
you heated up this poker, והכה בו, v'hika bo, and you hit
somebody with it right you know right near the right near this
place where he already had a wound. ונפק ביה חצי גריס אחר,
v'nafak bei chatzi gris acher, and now he there's another spot the
size of a half גריס. gris. So combined they're enough. מאי? mai?
What's the law? חבטה קדים? chavata kadim? Do we say the wound
came first and אתי הבלא ומבטליה ati havala u'mevatlei and then it
got burnt by the heat and therefore its status is that of
a מכוה, michva, a burn? מבטלא ליה לחבתא mvatla lei l'chavata והוי
ליה שחין
ומכוה v'havei lei shchin u'michva it would first have been a שחין
shchin and then a מכוה michva דלא מצטרפין d'lo mitztarfin and they
don't combine או דלמא הבלא קדים odilma havala kadim or do we
say the heat comes first ואתיא חבתא ומבטלא ליה להבלא v'atya chavata
u'mvatla lei l'havala and then the wound came and nullified it the
heat והוי ליה שחין ושחין
ומצטרפין v'havei lei shchin v'shchin u'mitztarfin it would be a שחין shchin
and שחין shchin and it would combine. So basically all of that
was a long way of creating a נפקא מינה nafka mina and
all this is a digression from שחיטה shechita with a hot knife,
but basically the point is like this: שחין shchin and מכוה michva
have the exact same הלכה. halacha. The only way it matters how
you categorize it is because the principle is that you cannot combine
half the size of one with half the size of the other.
The minimum size has to come from only one type of a
wound. So we want to know when you hit somebody with this
hot poker, which is it? We know that the הלכה halacha is
that if something is both, it goes by the last, so what
do we say happened? Did it first become a wound and then
become a burn or first a burn and then a wound? That
will determine the last thing will determine its status and the relevance
is if that wound appears right next to another thing that's half
a size and this is half a size will they combine? So
will they combine means are they put in the same category? So
we have to know if this thing that was hit with a
fire hot thing which came first. Now it's different than the knife
because now at least we understand why it's related to the knife.
The knife you have, it's sharp, it's very sharp. So there we
can say with sort of you know with assertiveness that the cutting
comes before the heat. But here where it's about you know banging
somebody, so you know the heat and the bang occur at the
same time. So which one do we think affects the body first?
I mean if anything certainly I would say the skin reacts more
to the heat initially and the wounding of the black and blue
whatever comes afterwards due to the impact. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. Okay. או דלמא ואתיא חבתא ומבטלא ליה להבלא והוי
ליה שחין ושחין ומצטרפין תא שמע. odilma v'atya chavata u'mvatla lei l'havala
v'havei lei shchin v'shchin u'mitztarfin ta shma. Come and hear. דאמר רבי
זירא אמר שמואל, d'amar Rabbi Zeira amar Shmuel, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
says in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, ליבן סכין ושחט בה שחיטתו
כשרה. liben sakin v'shachat bah shechitatos k'sheira.
So this is what we started with, that if you sharpened a
knife, excuse me, you heated a knife and you shechted with it,
it's a good שחיטה. shechita. חידודה קודמת לליבונה. chiduda kodemes l'libuna.
The sharpness preceded the heat. So first it cuts and then it
burns. אלמא חבתא קדים. alma chavata kadim. You see the wounding comes
first. So the גמרא Gemara says no that obviously doesn't prove anything.
חידוד שאני. chidud shani. Sharpness is different. If you have a sharp
knife obviously the cutting will precede the impact of the heat. But
when it's about impact we don't know which comes first. תא שמע.
ta shma. Come and hear. So we have an explicit ברייתא beraita
that directly addresses our case. ליבן שפוד והיכה בו. liben shipud v'hika
bo. If you heated up a poker and you smote, you know
smacked somebody with it, נידון משום מכוות אש. nidon mishum michvas eish.
It's considered to be a burn. אלמא חבתא קדים. alma chavata kadim.
So you see the wounding comes first and then the burn which
is pretty strange you would think. So the גמרא Gemara also is
not happy with it. The גמרא Gemara is not inclined to say
that. So the גמרא Gemara says no התם נמי דברזי מרזא דהיינו
חידוד. hasam nami d'barzi marza d'hainu chidud.
There also what you did is you made a point on the
poker. You took the poker, it wasn't like the edge was sharp
you know but the tip of it was pointed. So there if
you made it a pointy poker and you jabbed somebody with it
obviously even if it was boiling, even if it was hot, obviously
the you know the point, what would that be called, the puncture,
thank you, the puncturing preceded the impact of the heat. So there
clearly the heat comes last. But we still haven't answered our question
when it's just with the blunt force of it and the heat.
You know there it still stands to reason that the first impact
would be perceived of as being the heat and the second impact
would be perceived of as being the blunt force. So the גמרא
Gemara does not resolve that question.
Bobby. Anybody concerned about the guy getting smacked?
Oh of course the guy, but from a legal perspective we first
have to resolve this issue because of damage.
What's the נפקא מינה nafka mina of this?
I already said for how do you categorize it for צרעת? tzara'at?
Right? Is it a wound or is it an injury or is
it a burn in terms of does it combine with another spot
to make צרעת? tzara'at?
But what I'm talking about what about the damage what Bobby was
saying?
That will be discussed, whatever damage is caused is caused. It doesn't
matter whether you call it a wound or a burn, we look
at the totality of what you did. It doesn't, right, there's no
halachic difference to how you categorize it for issues of damages. Right.
And if the guy has a heart attack and drops dead is
that considered murder?
That's an interesting question which is what happens if yes, if somebody
is wounded and then dies later as a result of complications or
shock, how much is that considered an act of murder, is that
considered a later cause? So that is discussed in other גמרות Gemaras
but that's not our issue now. Okay.
Alright. So now we are done with that digression about צרעת tzara'at
but we are focusing as we see at least now we are
focusing on the act of שחיטה shechita itself. It's actually quite interesting
since our משנה mishna actually is talking about who are the people
qualified to do שחיטה, shechita, that the גמרא Gemara is using an
opportunity to collect a couple of sort of not so random but
whatever, a couple of statements about the act of שחיטה shechita which
actually comes later in the מסכת maseches on other משניות. mishnayos. So
I don't exactly know why the גמרא gemara does it right now
unless the גמרא gemara is sort of again wants to introduce a
מסכת masechet with sort of bring up some relevant material right at
the beginning. But we are moving from the focus of our משנה
mishnah which are the people involved. So let's take a look.
Yes, Azba, what did we just read?
You would have
thought
it would ask the exact case that happened when a person dies.
And then if I told you that
you had a hot poker and smacked somebody with it and they
died.
Right. Your instinct probably would be that they died from the force,
not from the heat, which would
have proved the case better.
And it's also the case that we're talking about lethal force in
both cases. Lethal. First of all, it's not clear it's lethal, it
could be lethal.
שחיטה shechitah is obviously lethal. Right. So if you took the case
of צרעת tzara'at is not lethal, the whole point of צרעת tzara'at
is the guy's alive.
So why are they introducing צרעת, tzara'at, why don't they say a
guy
came and smacked somebody else, sorry a woman came and smacked somebody
else like you with a heated poker.
Are they dying from the heat or are they dying from the
blow? Right. Because that's not, I think that that's not as analogous
to the שחיטה shechitah case. The שחיטה shechitah case is not what
is exactly happening at the spot of impact. Is it the knife
cutting the סימנים simanim or is the heat
cutting the סימנים?
simanim?
So here too, you have a particular wound. Was that wound
primarily first made by the impact or first made by the heat?
If somebody dies as a result that's not just a question about
this wounding right here, what did it. That's like the more macro
sense of what resulted from the whole act. So it's not directly
analogous. I mean it's a good question, but I'm just saying it's
not directly analogous to the שחיטה shechitah question.
Move the wound above the shoulders.
Well, that's analogous. Yeah, but again, but there's no, but halachically it
doesn't matter. I mean halachically if somebody killed somebody, what do we
care if it was through heat or through or through impact?
It's not sort of the narrow issue the גמרא gemara cares about
which is where would it matter if I determined whether it was
heat or whether it was the bluntness or whether it was the
sharpness. So it's looking for something somewhat similar to the שחיטה shechitah
case. All right, so now the גמרא gemara continues. אמר רב נחמן
Amar Rav Nachman אמר רבה בר אבוה amar Rabbah bar Avuha סכין
של עבודת כוכבים. sakkin shel avodat kochavim. Now we get into very
interesting cases which are very relevant להלכה l'halachah and not just about
שחיטה. shechitah. You have a knife that is used for
idolatry, okay, that's not so common, but some of the principles are.
So you have a knife that was used for idolatry, whether it
was used to שחט shecht animals for sacrifices or in other types
of ways, cutting things for the idol. But let's assume שחט shecht
animals for sacrifices. מותר לשחוט בה ואסור לחתוך בה בשר. Mutar lishchot
bah v'assur lachtoch bah basar.
So what's the rule? The first question is that something used in
idolatry you cannot derive any benefit. So you've got this knife, it
was used in idolatry you can't derive benefit. You can still use
it as a שחיטה shechitah knife, but you can't use it to
chop your meat. Why not? Either way you're deriving benefit. So let's
take a look. מותר לשחוט בה Mutar lishchot bah you can use
it to שחט, shecht, מקלקל הוא mekalkel hu
because you are actually destroying, because an animal is better alive than
dead. ואסור V'assur I'll unpack that in a minute, ואסור לחתוך בה
בשר, v'assur lachtoch bah basar, but you can't use it to cut
your meat, מתקן הוא. metakken hu. Once you have meat, so to
cut it up into usable pieces that's actually doing you a benefit.
So you're deriving benefit from using it to chop your meat but
you're not deriving benefit from a שחיטה shechitah knife. Now for us,
that's crazy. Obviously if you wouldn't be deriving benefit from שחט shechting
it, why would you be שחט? shechting? Why are people in the
business? Why do you pay a שוחט? shochet? So I don't really
have a fully satisfying answer. The best I can say is that
this obviously reflects an agricultural society which does not eat meat too
often as opposed to us where we have an entire meat industry.
So we have a meat industry, of course, the whole purpose of
the whole thing is to make money and the animal are really
what they are is like just are about to become meat. The
whole purpose is to become meat. In an agricultural society, primarily
you use your chickens for laying eggs and your goats and your
cows for milk and for wool, the sheep for wool or whatever.
And when it gets to a certain point where maybe there's a
special occasion and you want to eat meat, so you're going to
eat meat even though maybe it's not the best economic use of
this
thing because it's a special שמחה. simchah. Or that the animal is
old and out using its purpose, that's when you שחט. shecht. But
normally שחיטה shechitah is not considered to be like
the productive use of the animal. The productive use of the animal
is more in its larger agricultural context. So again, I think it's
hard for us to
understand, but I will just share with you when I was in
Senegal, I had the opportunity to be at a baby
naming, and the whole week we were seeing them run around with
these goat herds and cows or whatever and there for the baby
naming they actually slaughtered a goat, it was a sheep, I forget,
I think a sheep, which was like a very big deal. Actually
it was very interesting because then they did כיסוי הדם kisuy hadam
except that for the תורה Torah it's only for a חיה chayah
and not for a
בהמה. behemah. Anyway, the point being that okay, there's a very special
occasion we're going to slaughter a sheep and have meat, but that's
not necessarily the best economic use of that sheep. You don't, you
know, in an agricultural society I think meat was really a luxury
and it was not seen as the best economic use. Still all
in all you would say when a person actually goes decide they
want meat for whatever the reason is, you are deriving benefit from
using this knife. So it's a very fascinating גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that's
hard for us to get our heads around. Really speaks about a
very different type of societal reality and economic reality that שחיטה shechita
*Shechita* was not seen as a תיקון *Tikun*, it was seen as
a קלקול *Kilkul*, yes.
Could you say that at this point once you've done the שחיטה
shechita *Shechita* it's still אסור *Assur*? Right you still have מליחה *Melicha*,
כיסוי הדם *Kisui HaDam*. So at this point it's part of the
process, even though you've advanced the process but you have right now
you've taken it from live animal to dead animal that you can't,
that's not usable right now. Right. That's an interesting point. So it's
not even immediately usable in this state.
That's an interesting way to also make it a little more understandable
but we'll see in the גמרא Gemara... *Gemara* how the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* nuances it which I'm not sure would fit into your model
but that's an interesting possibility. So let's take a look how the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. So אמר
רבא *Amar Rava* and רבא *Rava* says פעמים ששוחט אסור *Peamim Sheshochet
Assur*. There are times when שחיטה shechita *Shechita* is forbidden when you
actually are deriving benefit. What? When is that? במסוכנת *Bimesukenet*. If the
animal is ill and actually you know is about to die. So
that would be a case where you actually would say this animal
has outused its usefulness, you know you don't want it to die
on you because if it dies on you without שחט shechted *Shecht*-ing
it you don't even get the meat out of this. So actually
by שחט shechted *Shecht*-ing it you're salvaging the meat. Okay, so that
doesn't work with your model.
It doesn't, does that work at all?
What?
Oh it's not a טרפה treifa *Treifah*, it's just ill. It doesn't
actually have a wound. Okay so מסוכנת *Mesukenet* is so right a
טרפה treifa *Treifah* actually has to have a wound. So this is
an animal that's old and dying, it's not serving any purpose and
by שחט shacht *Shecht*-ing it you're salvaging the meat. Okay so I
guess according to you it could still work with your model because
in its current stage it's not serving any purpose anyway and at
least once you שחט shachting *Shecht* it it's on the road of
becoming purposeful. Okay so that would be a case where you're really
benefiting by שחט shacht *Shecht*-ing it. ומחתך מותר *Umchatach Muttar*. There are
times when chopping the meat is permissible, where it actually is counterproductive.
What is that? באטמי דקיימי לקורבנא *Batmei Dekaymi Lekorbana*. When you have
nice cuts of meat that are appropriate to give as a gift,
like you've got a whole you know a
whole what's like a nice cut? A whole anyway, a whole thigh
or something, a whole rib roast, and then you come and you
cut it up you know to turn that into hamburger you're not
helping anything. So sometimes cutting is actually hurting and sometimes שחיטה shchita.
*Shechita* is helping. Okay so that's the question about whether you're deriving
benefit but again the fascinating aspect that שחיטה shechita. *Shechita* was not
considered to be necessarily deriving benefit. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
ותיפוק ליה משום שמנונית דאיסורא *Vetippok Lei Mishum Shamnunit Deissura*. And now
we get into general כשרות kashrus *Kashrut* questions. Who cares about the
fact that you can't derive benefit? Let's talk about another point. This
has been used to שחט shacht *Shecht* animals, or not שחט shacht
*Shecht*, to slaughter animals. So it's got טרפות treifos *Treifot* on the
knife. The assumption is we'll talk in a minute whether the knife
absorbs into it, but the assumption is that you know knives were
very hard to clean, they were constantly used with meat and with
fat, so that stuff was because they were serrated or whatever, so
that stuff was considered to always be on unless you really did
a vigorous job of cleaning. So if you're using this knife that
was used for you know slaughtering animals, so even if they were
כשר kasher *Kosher* animals but they're not הלכתית *Halachically* being slaughtered. So
the meat so you know the meat's fat is whatever non-כשר kasher
*Kosher* fat, it's נבילה *Neveilah* fat and נבילה *Neveilah* meat is on
your knife and now you're שחט shacht, *Shecht*-ing your other stuff or
cutting your other stuff, you're transferring the טרפה treifa, *Treifah*. So why
is that allowed? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says בחדשה *Bechadasha*. Ah,
it's not a knife that's been used already for עבודה זרה *Avoda
Zara*, it's a new knife that's been designated for עבודה זרה *Avoda
Zara*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says חדשה *Chadasha* new? בין רבי
ישמעאל בין רבי עקיבא *Bein Rabbi Yishmael Bein Rabbi Akiva*, whether רבי
ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that debate if an
idol is made and not worshipped is it forbidden? Does it have
to be worshipped or not? They're only debating an idol, but משמשי
עבודת כוכבים *Meshamshei Avodat Kochavim*, things that are used with idolatry, הן
*Hen* that's what this knife is. ומשמשי עבודת כוכבים *Umeshamshei Avodat Kochavim*
and things used with idolatry אינם אסורים עד שיעבדו *Einam Assurim Ad
Sheyiavdu*. Everybody agrees has to actually be used. So don't tell me
it's a brand new knife. We wouldn't have had our discussion with
a new knife, a new knife would not have been considered forbidden.
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says all right, two answers. Number one,
איבעית אימא *Iba'it Eima* if you want I'll say דפסיק ביה גאזא
לעבודת כוכבים *Depasik Bei Gaza L'avodat Kochavim*. You didn't use it for
slaughtering animals for עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*, you used it to chop
wood for עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*. Okay, so it doesn't have any
meat you know sort
of caked on it, any fat and it's not a problem. All
right, that's what we call an אוקימתא *Okimta* which is like you
know a way out, a cheap answer. ואיבעית אימא *Veba'it Eima* if
you want I'll say בישנה שלבנה באור *Beyeshana Shelivna Ba'or*.
Yes, it's a knife that was used for עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*,
but you cleaned it. You you got it white-hot in the fire,
there's again getting your knife white-hot, and way to remove all the
שמוץ, so you cleaned the knife and it's not a problem. But
now we are shifting into the question of forget idolatry issues and
deriving benefit, how do you deal with transfer of טריפות, treifus, you
know, from the knife and then back to the food? And this
gets to general כשרות kashrut, issues about how things absorb and transfer
taste. So that's what we're going to turn to right now. איתמר,
itmar, it was said: השוחט בסכין של עובדי כוכבים, ha-shocheit be-sakin shel
ovdei kochavim, again, you're using a knife of non-Jews.
Notice, by the way, the phrase is different. Before it was סכין
של עבודת כוכבים, sakin shel avodas kochavim, knife of idolatry was the
previous case, and there the issue was deriving benefit. Here it's סכין
של עובדי כוכבים, sakin shel ovdei kochavim, a knife of non-Jews. Okay,
so here it's not about a knife of idolatry, but a knife
used by non-Jews. So here the question is not deriving benefit, the
only issue is the טריפות treifus that might be on the knife.
Okay, so סכין של גויים. sakin shel goyim.
So גויים, goyim, right? עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim clearly anyway, almost all
the time the גמרא Gemara. refers to non-Jews in the original text,
it's גויים, goyim, עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim is a later censorship. Okay,
so here clearly it is a different issue, it is a knife
of non-Jews. רב אמר קולף ורבה בר בר חנה אמר מדיח. Rav
amar koleif ve-Rabba bar Bar Chana amar madiach. So you שחט shacht?
it. So the question is, does the gook, very technical term, that
was on the knife, the non-kosher stuff that was on the knife
because it was used by non-Jews, does that transfer to the place
in which you're doing the שחיטה shechita and therefore the בית השחיטה,
beis ha-shechita, what it's called, the place of the cutting itself has
some non-kosher food there and you have to remove it or not
if you want to eat from that meat where exactly the knife
touched. So the first answer is קולף, koleif, you have to peel
away, you know, you have to cut off the outer surface. You
are afraid that something transferred of the meat. Right, you שחט shacht
the meat. So exactly where your knife touched the meat, and this
knife was taken from non-Jews, so it has maybe some טריפות treifus
on it, it transfers to the place where you cut. So if
you want to eat exactly from the neck of the animal where
the שחיטה shechita occurred, you have to remove the surface because that's
where the knife touched and transferred. And one position, and the other
position says no, רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar Bar Chana says
מדיח, madiach, just rinse it off. So yes, maybe some surface thing
transferred, but it didn't get into the skin, it's on the surface,
so just rinse it off. This is a similar question of like
if you buy your fish from, you know, in the supermarket, right?
So if you know that it's kosher fish, let's say you see
the scales or you see it's salmon or tuna, you can see
it, and you're concerned, did they clean the knife well? Did they
not clean the knife well? Do you have to take off just
the outer, you know, can you just rinse it? Or do you
actually have to like scrape off, you know, some amount of the
surface where the cut was made? Bobby.
I'm just wondering again, I'm going back to the burning and the
point of the knife and the cutting.
Yeah, we're not there anymore, but okay.
No, I understand that, but there's I think there's a relationship because
you have a knife, right? Right. You have a point of a
knife. Yeah. A point of a knife can be cleaned.
Yeah, but we're not talking about the point, we're talking about the
cutting edge, the whole length of it. And that's exactly where we're
afraid that stuff cakes on and is hard to clean. Now again,
a שחיטה shechita, knife is not serrated. So it is interesting that
we're concerned even there, you know, that stuff gets, but but again
they also did not have stainless steel, they didn't have, you know,
you know, the metal itself was, you know, stuff got in and
had crevices and was harder. So all right, so let's take a
look at what the גמרא...
Gemara Hang on, you brought up fish. Can you purchase fish?
Well, I'm not going to answer that right now, let's see how
the גמרא Gemara. resolves it, okay? We can I'll talk to you
later, but let's see what at least that's a direct analogy.
Yes, the knife has to be has
can't have any nicks, but what about on the side?
Yeah, the side can, right? The sharpness can't, but the side can
have like whatever, you know. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, לימא בהא קמיפלגי, lema be-hai ka-mifligi,
let's say this is what they debate. גמרא Gemara. סבר בית השחיטה
צונן, savar beis ha-shechita tzonein, one person holds that the place where
you're slaughtering is cold, ומר סבר בית השחיטה רותח, u-mar savar beis
ha-shechita roseiach,
that it's hot, because the heat of the just of the skin
of the animal and the blood is coming up but whatever the
heat of the skin of the inner inner heat of the animal.
So why? Because halachically, again, we're assuming this knife has stuff on
the surface, so everybody agrees you have to rinse off because something
will transfer on the surface. But does it get into? So normally
we assume halachically things only absorb into them with the use of
heat. So therefore the question is, is it considered to be hot
enough for halachic definition of what is hot to say that it
absorbed in? And maybe that's what they debate. So the גמרא Gemara
says לא, lo, not necessarily. דכולי עלמא בית השחיטה רותח הוא, de-chulei
alma beis ha-shechita roseiach hu, I could say they all agree that
it is considered hot. So why would I say it does not
get absorbed in? מאן דאמר קולף, man de-amar koleif, the one that
says you have to peel away the surface layer, שפיר, shapir, that
we understand. ומאן דאמר מדיח, u-man de-amar madiach, the one that says
just rinse it, איידי דטרידי סימנים לאפוקי דם לא בלעי. aidi de-tridi
simanim le-apukei dam lo bali. Since the גמרא Gemara. has this type
of logic in a number of places, which we'll see later in
the מסכתא, masechta, since the neck and the whatever is busy spurting
out its
blood and you know, it doesn't have. at the same time. That's
one reason you might say it remains on the surface. איכא דאמרי,
Ika d'amri, some say the opposite. דכולי עלמא בית השחיטה צונן, de-kulei
alma beit hashchita tzonen, they all would agree that it's not considered
hot. מאן דאמר מדיח, Man de-amar madiach, if you say rinse it,
שפיר, shapir, that makes sense. מאן דאמר קולף, Man de-amar kolef, the
one that says that actually some gets absorbed inside, אגב דוחקא דסכינא,
agav duchka de-sakina, because of the pressure of the knife, בלע בלע,
bala bala, it absorbs. Okay, so some stuff gets in not through
heat but through pressure of the knife. I want to take one
minute to talk about two important halachic principles that may or may
not come out of this גמרא. Gemara One is the question of
defining heat. So a number of ראשונים Rishonim assume that the heat
you need for absorption is the type of heat we talk about
by שבת, Shabbat, which is יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, right,
the type of heat that you put your hand in and you
like jerk it out because it's so hot. So the question is
how hot is יד סולדת בו yad soledet bo halachically makes a
big difference for כשרות, for שבת, Shabbat, and so on. So a
number of פוסקים poskim say, you know, don't try to translate that
into Fahrenheit or Celsius. The rabbis told you how to determine it:
you stick your finger in and you see if you can hold
it. If not, you pull it out and that's how we determine
it. But there are always those who want to translate it into,
you know, very quantifiable. So they look at this גמרא. Gemara They
say since there's a debate whether the בית השחיטה beit hashchita is
considered hot or not, that means that it's right at the edge
of what the halachic definition of hot would be, or else you
wouldn't be debating it. So they go let's determine how hot that
is and that will tell us what at least the lower lowest
possible limit of יד סולדת בו yad soledet bo is. So they
did this, I think it comes out to something pretty low like
102, 106, something like that degrees. Now the problem is the problem
with that is that a number of ראשונים Rishonim disagree and actually
say that heat for absorbing taste does not have to be יד
סולדת בו. yad soledet bo. That the principles of יד סולדת בו,
yad soledet bo, whatever, those are שבת Shabbat principles, but the heat
for absorbing taste can actually be lower and therefore this whole גמרא
Gemara does not become relevant then for determining יד סולדת בו. yad
soledet bo. So that's one interesting aspect of this גמרא. Gemara Is
it a basis for determining the principle of יד סולדת בו? yad
soledet bo? Another question is what do we think about knives? Do
knives, this phrase about דוחקא דסכינא, duchka de-sakina, the pressure of a
knife, do we think that that can transfer taste, transfer something in
deep into something all by itself? So that's one thing the גמרא
says is a possibility; even without heat it can transfer. תוספות Tosafot
says no, but based on other גמרות, Gemarot, no, no, no, even
that wouldn't do it by itself. Because here there's not no heat,
it is hot. It might not be hot enough. So it's something
that is close to being hot enough plus the pressure of the
knife. But can the pressure of the knife do it all on
its own? That's not so clear from this גמרא. So that gets
back to our fish question, right, the fish which is totally cold.
So first of all, let's assume that I'm worried that there's gook
on the knife. If I'm not worried there's gook on the knife,
the whole thing isn't relevant. So do I have to actually, can
I just rinse it or do I have to peel it away?
Well, am I concerned that pressure of a knife without any heat
will actually get some of the gook deep into it or will
it all remain on the surface? So part of that's a question
about how do you פסקן pasken this גמרא and do you think
that it's just pressure of the knife or תוספות Tosafot says no,
it's pressure of the knife together with a certain amount of heat.
So some very interesting halachic issues arise from this גמרא. Okay,
and so רבקה, Rivka, the short answer to the question is whether
you have to just rinse the fish or scrape off the surface
is that it's a debate based on the issues that we just
raised here.
But either way you're saying it's permissible.
Yeah, as long as certainly if you scrape off the place of
the cut, it's not a problem at all. You know, so but
and according it might if they basically really do clean the knife
beforehand and so on, which you know, rinse it and whatever,
it's probably fine to just even rinse the fish.
A lot of many fish stores say they use separate knives.
Right, right.
So then there's no need for kosher.
I would generally say that if you want to be פרום, frum,
you scrape it, but certainly if you just rinse it off, and
especially if they're saying they're cleaning the knives and saying they're using
separate knives, you can do it. But the big issue is that
trusting them on fish that is not discernible by its skin and
that is not and that you're not seeing the fins and the
scales. There was a recently a major thing in the New York
Times, I actually read something similar five years ago where there's a
tremendous amount of intentional mislabeling of of they're cheating because of of
the labeling of the fish. So that's a different story. Okay, so
now the גמרא goes on, okay, סכין טריפה, sakin treifa, let's say
the knife was used to שחט shacht a טריפה treifa animal, not
intentionally, but this will always happen. You're שחט shacht and one of
the animals becomes טריפה. treifa. So now the stuff on your knife
is, you know, fat and meat from from an animal that was
טריפה. treifa. Not טריפה treifa in the sense of like like not
a cow, but טריפה treifa in the sense like it had an
actual טריפות treifot on it, which will happen in a normal process
of שחיטה. shechita Can I continue using this knife to שחט shacht
other animals or do I have to worry about the stuff that's
on the surface or got absorbed? So now the stuff on your
knife is fat and meat from an animal that was טריף. treif.
Not טריף treif in the sense of like not a cow, but
טריף treif in the sense like it had an actual טרפה on
it, which will happen in a normal process of שחיטה. shechita Can
I continue using this knife to שחט shacht, other animals or do
I have to worry about the stuff that's on the surface or
got absorbed in the knife? So פליגי רב אחא ורבינא, polgi Rav
Aha v'Ravina, they debated it. חד אמר בחמין וחד אמר בצונן. chad
amar bachamin v'chad amar b'tzonin.
How do I have to כשר kosher this knife? So one said
you have to use heat to כשר kosher it, that you assume
that the gook got absorbed into the knife itself. And one said:
No, no, no, you can just wash it off with cold water.
The gook only got on the surface of the knife. So before
we were talking about does the gook get into the skin of
the animal. Here we're talking about does the טרפות treifos get into
the metal of the knife or remain on the surface. והלכתא v'hilchasa
and the הלכה halacha is אפילו בצונן afilu b'tzonin that you can
rinse it off just with cold water. ואיכא בליסה דפרצא למיחפרה v'ika
blisa d'partza l'michpara and if you have a piece of wool or
of material in order to clean it, like steel wool or something
like that, then לא צריך, lo tzarich, you don't even need cold
water because it's just surface and you can get the stuff off
from the surface. So here it basically says it's somewhat analogous to
the other question, but before we were talking about was the place
of the שחיטה shechita. hot enough for the stuff to get into
the skin. Here we're talking about was it hot enough for the
טרפות to get into the knife. And the basic answer is: No,
it doesn't get into the knife, it only remains on the surface.
רש"י Rashi points out that doesn't necessarily resolve the previous question because
again, here's an interesting question about חז"ל's Chazal physics or whatever you
call it, that flesh is obviously more absorbent than metal. So the
place of the שחיטה shechita might be hot enough that gook will
get into flesh, but not hot enough to make the problematic thing
you're שחטing shacht get into the metal. So here we say it's
at the surface of the metal. רש"י Rashi asks another question, which
is why do you have to talk about טרפה to get non-כשר
kosher stuff? Every time you שחט, shacht there's non-כשר kasher stuff. What's
non-כשר kasher every time that the knife is coming into contact with
every time you שחט? Blood. The blood. Why are we not concerned
that the blood gets into the knife? So רש"י Rashi says because
blood basically doesn't isn't as adhesive as the fat and the meat,
so that we assume just slides off and is not a problem.
The problem is when you שחט fat meat. Well, yeah, but you
could have said you have to כשר kosher your knife between every
שחיטה, but we don't say that. But again, it's very interesting the
different types of physics that the rabbis apply. The metal is harder
to get into than the flesh, the blood doesn't get in as
deep as the meat and as the fat and so on. Okay.
So let's just read a little bit more. ולמאן דאמר בחמין u'leman
d'amar bachamin
and the one that says you have to use hot water to
כשר kosher. the knife, מאי טעמא mai ta'ama why? משום דקבולי
איסורא, mishum d'kabulei issura, because it's absorbing the forbidden stuff, שחט טריפה.
shachat treifa. So the גמרא says: דהיתרא נמי בלע? d'heteira nami bala?
So if that's true, even when you שחט a non-טריפה, treifa, as
you start שחטing the animal's forbidden, why? The animal is right now
אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, it's non-שחטed meat. So every single
time you שחט, why aren't we concerned that even if it's a
כשר animal, that before you finish the שחיטה some of the taste
of the meat got in when it was not yet שחטed meat?
So the גמרא says, אבר מן החי אימת בלע. eiver min hachai
eimas bala. נמי בלע אבר מן החי, nami bala eiver min hachai,
it absorbs some of the taste of non-שחטed meat. So the גמרא
says, no. אימת בלע, eimas bala, when is it absorbing? לכי חמימא.
l'chi chamima. We had said before that you needed the heat, the
heat of the בית השחיטה. beis hashechita. So אימת דקא חמימא, eimas
d'ka chamima, when is the knife sort of in the presence of
the heat of the animal? לכי גמרה שחיטה l'chi gamra shechita when
the שחיטה is done, then it's deep into the neck and it's
surrounded by the heat of the animal.
ההיא שעתא היתרא הואי. hahi sha'ata heteira havai. Then it's permissible. So
it will never absorb the taste of the meat before the שחיטה.
The concern of the knife getting into the metal is from the
heat of the neck, and that's only after the knife is deep
into the neck and after the animal is כשר. So the only
issue is when the animal was a טרפה, did it absorb then
and did it get just on the surface? So again the basic
upshot of this seems to be that the stuff remains on the
surface, doesn't get in, the heat is not enough certainly for the
knife, and it would seem even for the שחיטה neck of the
animal as well transferring in the other way, that there's a question
how hot that is and a question about the pressure of the
knife and whether it's enough to rinse it or just scrape it
off. And as I said, two very relevant הלכתי halachic issues. One
is defining יד סולדת, yad soledes, is this relevant, and the other
is the question about in general when things have no heat, are
we concerned about the pressure of the knife getting into stuff any
deeper than just at the surface? Okay. So let's
just read a little bit more.